Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge

August 19, 2016

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA

Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science *Aug 2008 – May 2011*

Purdue University, USA GPA: 3.94/4 Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 - May 2008

PSG College of Technology GPA: 9.55/10 Anna University, India

Experience

Research Associate, University of Cambridge

Dec 2014 - present Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Developing Multicore OCaml under the OCaml Labs initiative in the Computer Laboratory.

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014 Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University West Lafayette, IN, USA Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Aug 2012 - Dec 2012 Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) Aug 2011 – Dec 2011

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge Feb 2012 - May 2012 Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D)

May 2010 - Aug 2010 Advisor: Daniel Waddington San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language - a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Dec 2007 - Apr 2008 Advisor: Sankar Chnab Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell Jun 2016 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones J2 Journal of Functional Programming (JFP) Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventu-Mar 2016 ally Consistent Key-Value Stores J1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin, 39(1): 52 64, March 2016 MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML Nov 2014 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan J0 Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 - 674 **Efficient Sessions** Feb 2013 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster J-1 Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 - 167 Invited paper Conference Publications **Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores** Jun 2015 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan C7 International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Rx-CML:** A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C6 Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL) A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C5 Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award **Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness** Jun 2012 C4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM) **Composable Asynchronous Events** Jun 2011 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan C3

June 2010

Sep 2009

Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication C1 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan

Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster

International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION)

International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)

Workshop Publications

C2

W4	Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop	Sep 2016
W3	Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop	Sep 2016
W2	Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop	Sep 2016
W1	Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop	Sep 2015
W0	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013
W-1	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011
W-2	The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop	Sep 2010
W-3	Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)	Jan 2010
❖ Technical Reports and Drafts		
T2	Featherweight Threads for Communication KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018	Nov 2011

Teaching/Advising

- Guest Lectures:
 - Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent 2015–16.
 - Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas 2015–16.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
 - Algorithms, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent 2015–16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Michaelmas 2015–16.
 - Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
 - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
 - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:

- James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Michelmas 2015 present.
- Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 present.
- Theo Laurent, ENS de Lyon, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
- Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

Talks

OCaml Platform: Update Nov 2015 OCaml Consortium Meeting Paris, France Multicore OCaml: Update Nov 2015 OCaml Developer's Meeting Paris, France

Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects

Sep 2015 OCaml Workshop 2015 Vancouver, Canada

Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

PhD Defense Purdue University Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming Mar 2014

Invited Lecture

Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014

PADL 2014 Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud ML Workshop 2013

Boston, MA A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 MARC 2012 RWTH Aachen

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

ISMM 2012, Beijing Jun 2012 Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge May 2012

Lightweight Concurrency in GHC

May 2012 Wrestling Wednesdays Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction COORDINATION 2012

Jun 2012 CWI Amsterdam

Dec 2014

San Diego, CA

Sep 2013

Professional Service

- Program Committee member: OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.